<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true mark of the beast, or, The present degeneracy of the Church of Rome from the faith once delivered to the saints a sermon on November 5, 1681 / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1620</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11876267</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11876267</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50257</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53985)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50257)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 504:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true mark of the beast, or, The present degeneracy of the Church of Rome from the faith once delivered to the saints a sermon on November 5, 1681 / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Hindmarsh..., and Walter Davis...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A sermon preached on the fifth of November.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50257:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50257:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRUE <hi>Mark of the Beaſt:</hi> OR THE PRESENT DEGENERACY <hi>OF THE Church of Rome</hi> FROM THE FAITH <hi>once delivered to the</hi> SAINTS.</p>
            <p>A SERMON on <hi>November</hi> 5. 1681.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD PELLING,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Martin</hi>'s <hi>Ludgate,</hi> and Chaplain to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quid Romae faciam? Mentiri neſcio.</hi> 
               <bibl>Juv. Sat. 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Can the</hi> Ethiopian <hi>change his</hi> skin, <hi>or the</hi> Leopard <hi>his</hi> ſpots? <hi>then may</hi> Ye <hi>alſo do Good, that are</hi> accuſtomed <hi>to do Evil.</hi> 
               <bibl>Jer. 13. <hi>v.</hi> 23.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Let no man</hi> deceive <hi>you by any means, for</hi> that <hi>day ſhall not</hi> come, <hi>except there come a</hi> falling away <hi>firſt, and that</hi> Man <hi>of</hi> Sin <hi>be</hi> revealed, <hi>the</hi> Son <hi>of</hi> Perdition: <hi>Who</hi> oppoſeth <hi>and</hi> exalteth himſelf above all <hi>that is</hi> called God, <hi>or that is</hi> worſhipped; <hi>ſo that</hi> He <hi>as</hi> God ſitteth <hi>in the</hi> Temple <hi>of</hi> God, ſhewing Himſelf that He is God.<bibl> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh</hi> at the <hi>Black-Bull</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> and <hi>Walter Davis</hi> in <hi>Amen Corner.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50257:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50257:2"/>
            <head>To his Grace, my ever Honoured and Dear Lord, CHARLES Duke of SOMERSET, Marqueſs and Earl of HERTFORD, Viſcount BEAUCHAMP, and Baron of TROWBRIDG.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SEldom do <hi>ſome men make</hi> any <hi>Comments,</hi> but they chuſe <hi>me</hi> for their <hi>Text.</hi> Since I preſented to your Grace a little Sermon preached on the <hi>30</hi> of <hi>January, Factious</hi> people have accuſed me of <hi>Partiality,</hi> for not Publiſhing this that was Preached on the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>November</hi> laſt; and thence the Charity of our Modern Bleſſed Saints, (who like the Old <hi>Neſtorians</hi> are<hi>—nati ad Calumniandum—</hi>rarely gifted in thoſe two Virtues, <hi>Lying</hi> and <hi>Slandering)</hi> hath concluded, that I am a <hi>ſecret friend</hi> to the <hi>Popiſh Intereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which manifeſt and groſs injury I have yet the leſs reaſon to repine at, ſince ſo many thouſands of men who are far my betters, have an equal ſhare of it, ſo that all who are <hi>not given to change,</hi> all who are <hi>not weary</hi> of a <hi>Happy Peace,</hi> all who <hi>Dread</hi> to be <hi>Slaves</hi> again to their <hi>Fellow-Subjects,</hi> all that are <hi>true friends</hi> to the <hi>Government Eſtabliſht in Church and State,</hi> all that <hi>love</hi> the <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>acquieſce</hi> in the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Counſels</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> all Ranks and Degrees of men, even Peers and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, who <hi>Abhorr</hi> the <hi>ſeditious</hi> practiſes of <hi>Ambitious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengefull</hi> and <hi>unquiet Spirits,</hi> are Libell'd under the notion of <hi>Tantivyes, Popiſhly affected, Papiſts in Maſquerade, Iriſh Bog-trotters,</hi> and under I know not how many <hi>Nick names</hi> more.</p>
            <p>Little do they conſider in the mean while, how they <hi>Diſhonour</hi> the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> and what great <hi>Service they do the Romaniſts,</hi> when they call every <hi>Honeſt</hi> man a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and make <hi>Knavery</hi> to be a <hi>Characteriſtical note of a</hi> TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E PROTESTANT.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:50257:3"/>
And though the <hi>Sons</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> be thus tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced as <hi>unfaithfull</hi> to their <hi>Mother,</hi> yet we hope the indifferent world will conſider, that none but <hi>they</hi> have <hi>effectually</hi> undertaken the defence of the <hi>Proteſtant Cauſe</hi> all a long. And 'tis obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that ſince the diſcovery of the late <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> whereas the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> hath both by <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>writing</hi> induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſly <hi>Laboured</hi> againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have <hi>Laboured</hi> with all their might and main againſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> which when men of <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> ſhall <hi>conſider,</hi> they will ſoon <hi>diſcern who</hi> they are amongſt us, that <hi>are the beſt friends to the Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to mine own particular, My Lord, I do <hi>ſincerely proteſt</hi> as in the <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>Eternal</hi> and <hi>Omniſcient God,</hi> that <hi>I have ever liv'd,</hi> and <hi>by Gods grace am reſolved to dy a true member of our Church as it is now Eſtabliſht.</hi> And for the reſt of my <hi>Brethren,</hi> the <hi>Conformable Clergy,</hi> they cannot be <hi>ſuſpected</hi> but either by <hi>Ignorant</hi> or by <hi>Ill men;</hi> it being impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for thoſe, who give their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeigned <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> to <hi>entertain</hi> any <hi>kind</hi> or <hi>favourable Opinion</hi> of thoſe <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Corruptions,</hi> which we <hi>juſtly Condemn</hi> in the <hi>Roman Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, to deal truly with your <hi>Grace;</hi> the <hi>onely Reaſon</hi> why this <hi>Sermon</hi> was <hi>not Publiſht before,</hi> was, becauſe I looked upon it as <hi>ſo inconſiderable a thing in compariſon</hi> of what has been done by <hi>men</hi> of <hi>Great Learning</hi> and <hi>True Worth,</hi> that I <hi>could not take</hi> the <hi>confidence</hi> to <hi>ſhew it</hi> the <hi>World.</hi> Some diſcourſes may be fit enough for the Pulpit, which may not be ſo fit for the Preſs; and ſuch I conceive this Diſcourſe to be. However ſince 'tis going abroad, it will not take up much room in the World; and this advantage I gain by it, an opportunity of preſenting my moſt Hearty Service and Duty to your Grace, and of profeſſing my ſelf, what I am, My Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Grace's moſt Obedient, Obliged, and Affectionate Servant and Chaplain, EDWARD PELLING.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 16, 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50257:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED ON The Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> 1681.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Rom. 1. 8.</bibl>
               <q>Firſt, I thank my God, through Jeſus Chriſt, for you all, that your Faith is ſpoken of throughout the whole World.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>YOu ſee by the Verſe preceding, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> directed this Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that <hi>then</hi> was: and you may be ſure, that the <hi>Modern Romaniſts</hi> have not failed to make the moſt uſe of this Text (more indeed by far, than the Apoſtle ever intended to give them occaſion of making;) for as it is their conſtant cuſtom, when they Comment upon the <hi>Fathers,</hi> if they meet with any <hi>little</hi> paſſage, though it be but the clink of a <hi>word,</hi> that ſeems to favour their Errors, to catch hold on it preſently, as if all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50257:4"/>
the world were their own, (whereas they <hi>abuſe</hi> the Writer all the while, and either willingly miſtake, or ſtudiouſly wreſt the place contrary to the true ſenſe of the Author:) ſo when they are Commenting upon the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> if they light upon any one Text, which with all their Art and Skill they can but take advantage by, to plead from it, and to Hallow their Impieties, they run away ſtrait with an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, glad that they have found a booty, a dainty and ſtrong Argument for their Cauſe.</p>
            <p>But if St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles, an Apoſtle, that together with <hi>Peter</hi> preached and ſuffered Martyrdome at <hi>Rome,</hi> an Apoſtle to whoſe Writings the Proteſtants do frequently Appeal, and whoſe Epiſtles ſome of the Romaniſts have been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angry with, becauſe they do too much favour the Hereticks (as they have been pleaſed to ſay;) if <hi>this</hi> Great man did ſo commend the Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as he doth in this Text; and if He ſpake ſo Honourably of it, as that it was admired by the whole world; we may reaſonably expect to hear enough of their Brags. And indeed, this is their Starting place, whence they run out into very high Encomiums of their Church, and they tell us of a great number of Ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> that <hi>join</hi> with them in their Applauſes: they would perſwade us, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> here doth not only <hi>Declare</hi> what the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was then, but moreover that he did <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> that it ſhould be an Excellent Church unto the worlds End, and that his Commendation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth as well the Chriſtians at <hi>Rome</hi> in his days, as their Poſterity and Succeſſors for ever. They
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50257:4"/>
tell us, that the Apoſtle pointeth to their Church, as to the Mother Church of the whole world, and that he extolleth their Faith, as that which all other Churches were to look upon, and mind, and obſerve as their Rule; that they were to account Her not their <hi>Siſter,</hi> but their <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendent;</hi> that they were from thenceforth to ſay after Her, and to ſeek for the Law of Chriſt at Her mouth, and in every particular to follow Her Directions: ſo that whoſoever in proceſs of time ſhould not be of Her Communion, he ought not to be look'd upon as a Catholick, or a Chriſtian, but as a Foreigner, and an Alien to the Covenant of Grace.</p>
            <p>Can any thing be Higher than this? and yet what a ſlight Pedeſtal is it, which this Tower of <hi>Babel</hi> ſtands upon? Indeed St. <hi>Paul</hi> had reaſon to Praiſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in His time, becauſe its Faith was Pure, Entire, and Uncorrupted then, and ſo continued for a conſiderable time after. Let it be granted too, (becauſe the words of <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccleſ. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> ſeem to argue it) that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were in His days <hi>of the ſame true Faith with the Biſhops of other Churches.</hi> Let it be allowed too, that even in <hi>Iraeneus</hi>'s time, that Church <hi>kept the Apoſtles</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. adv. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. lib</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Tradition;</hi> meaning, that <hi>Doctrine</hi> which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had once for all delivered unto the Saints. Nay, I ſee no danger if we go further yet, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that thoſe Commendations which St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyp. Ep.</hi> 55. <hi>Hier. Apol.</hi> 3. <hi>adv. Ruffin.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jerome,</hi> and others of the fourth Century gave of that Church, were not meer Complements; but that ſhe was ſo Faithful in the main, that ſhe could not eaſily, or would not willingly be guilty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50257:5"/>
of Perſidiouſneſs, eſpecially in caſes of moment: I ſay, Let us ſuppoſe all this, that for ſome Ages, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> continued a Virgin not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowr'd by any Hereticks; yet it will by no means follow, that ſhe did not proſtitute her Chaſtity in after Ages, or that it was not <hi>Poſſible</hi> for her ever to turn Harlot. There is no reaſon for that Fancy, that if men be once in a good State, they ſhall be ſo always; much leſs reaſon is there for that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that a Church which is once Pure, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be defiled: and yet this is the thing which many unwary Romaniſts now take for granted, that ſince the Faith of their Church was once right and ſound (which St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth here intimate, and confeſs) ſhe neither <hi>did</hi> nor <hi>could</hi> Adulterate and Corrupt it, and ſo, that it is as Sincere &amp; Pure now, as ever it was in the Apoſtles dayes. And accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this rate <hi>Cornelius à Lapide</hi> the Jeſuite, doth reckon in his notes upon my Text, <hi>That the Faith of the Roman Church was ſound in St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s time, amd ſo down to St.</hi> Jerome's <hi>time, and ſo by neceſſary conſequence unto this time; for never hitherto</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath any Hereſie tainted Rome, as it hath other Cities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Point neceſſary to be Examined, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Fallacy that highly deſerves to be Detected, for the good of ſuch Souls as are willing to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed. And therefore I ſhall take occaſion from the Text, and the Day, to ſhew you theſe following things in Order:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What that Faith was which St. <hi>Paul</hi> here commendeth.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:50257:5"/>
2. That it was poſſible for this their Faith to be altered and corrupted in After-ages.</item>
               <item>3. That the <hi>Ancient Faith</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath been <hi>de facto</hi> Actually corrupted.</item>
               <item>4. That a Reformation of thoſe Corruptions was on our ſide Juſtifiable.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And ſo in the laſt place we will leave it to the impartial world to conſider, whether thoſe violent Methods are juſtifiable, which the Romaniſts have uſed ſince the Reformation, for the Re-eſtabliſhment of thoſe Corruptions. And of theſe as briefly as I can.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What the Faith was which the Apoſtle here commendeth the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for, and which he ſaith was ſpoken of throughout the whole World. It is certain in the <hi>general,</hi> that the Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was not <hi>different</hi> from the Faith of other Churches: for as there was but <hi>One Lord,</hi> ſo there was but <hi>One Faith</hi> over the whole Chriſtian World, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 5. And the Reaſon why St. <hi>Paul</hi> with Thankfulneſs takes notice of the <hi>Romans</hi> Faith was, not becauſe it was <hi>Other,</hi> or more <hi>Excellent</hi> than that which was received in other places, but becauſe <hi>Rome,</hi> being the great Imperial City, whereunto the world was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to have recourſe, the Chriſtian Faith was likely thence to Diſſeminate it ſelf every where over all the parts of the Empire in a very ſhort time. Now if we enquire particularly what that Faith was, we ſhall find it to have been this, <hi>viz.</hi> A Confeſſion of the <hi>Neceſſary</hi> and <hi>Important</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Chriſtianity; A Belief of thoſe <hi>Main</hi> and <hi>Fundamental</hi> Truths, touching the Divine Nature
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50257:6"/>
and Authority of our Bleſſed Saviour, touching the things which he did and ſuffered for the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, and touching thoſe ineſtimable Bleſſings which wereconſequent hereunto, as the Sanctification of our hearts by the Holy Spirit, the Remiſſion of our Sins, and the Hope of an Happy Reſurrection to Eternal Life for Chriſt his ſake. Theſe are the Grand Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, and they are ſummed up in that ſhort Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Chriſtian Verities, which we call the Apoſtles Creed, becauſe (whether they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves compiled that Collection or no) it contains thoſe main Points and Doctrines which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles preached at <hi>Rome,</hi> and in all places beſide, as the only <hi>Credenda,</hi> or matters of Faith, that were abſolutely <hi>Neceſſary</hi> to Salvation.</p>
            <p>Of this we have Teſtimonies abundant: for when St. <hi>Paul</hi> preached at <hi>Athens,</hi> they were the <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> &amp; <hi>Subſtantial</hi> Doctrines of Chriſtianity which he taught, <hi>viz. Jeſus, and the Reſurrection,</hi> as St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 18. And when the great Apoſtle wrote to the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Church, he told them, what that <hi>Goſpel was which he had received himſelf, and which he had delivered unto them,</hi> and by <hi>which they were to be ſaved;</hi> And what was that Goſpel? why, a Collection ſtill of theſe Neceſſary matters of Faith, <hi>how that Chriſt died for our ſins, and that he was buried, and that he roſe again the third day, according to the Scriptures,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 1, 2, 3, 4. Nay, writing to That Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Ancient Faith we are now conſidering, he declares what that was, which he and the reſt of the Apoſtles made the common ſubject of their diſcourſes (to the Romans, and to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50257:6"/>
all other people) and ſtill it was of the neceſſary and prime matters of Faith; for <hi>This,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is the word of Faith which we preach, that if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in thine heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved,</hi> Rom. 10. 8, 9. Now can any thing be plainer than this, That the Faith which all the Apoſtles preach'd, which all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches receiv'd, and for which the Roman Church is here commended, was made up of thoſe principal Doctrines which at this day we find in our Creed?</p>
            <p>To theſe, were it neceſſary to add the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <note place="margin">Tert de veland. Virgin. &amp; de praſcrip. Atka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſ. in initio &amp; fine Symbol.</note> of Church-writers, I might inſtance in <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, Athanaſius,</hi> and divers more, who ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Creed, own'd it to have been the <hi>One, only, immoveable</hi> and <hi>ſufficient</hi> Rule which all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians went by; the Catholick Faith, and the Faith of all Churches in the world, which whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, was a right Catholick and ſound Believer. But to avoid prolixity, I ſhall only take notice of what we meet with in <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who lived in the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. adv. Haer. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.</note> very next age to the Apoſtles; for, rehearſing the Articles of the Creed, he tells us, that <hi>That</hi> was the Faith which the whole Church over the whole world had received <hi>from the Apoſtles and their Diſciples; that every Church held, taught, and kept with all diligence and care, and that the Churches in</hi> Germany, <hi>in</hi> Spain, <hi>in</hi> France, <hi>in the Eaſtern parts of</hi> Egypt, <hi>in</hi> Africk, <hi>and in the mid-land parts of the world</hi> (which takes in <hi>Rome</hi> too) <hi>did in His dayes believe no other Doctrines, than what were contained in the Apoſtles Creed, and that the Univerſal Church was</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50257:7"/>
               <hi>One, becauſe the Faith of every Church in the world was one and the ſame, and that none either taught more, or believed leſs, than that One Faith did amount unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas! in thoſe dayes the Creed of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians was a plain, eaſie and ſhort one; for they thought themſelves obliged to this only, to believe the Eſſentials of Chriſtianity, and to lead good lives; and it had been well for Chriſtendom, had after-ages taken no other care: but by multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Articles ſome have multiplyed Errors too; and as <hi>Seneca</hi> obſerved of the old World, that while men lived upon a <hi>Simple</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> ſort of Diet, they were very healthful and ſtrong; but <hi>multos morbos multa fercula fecerunt,</hi> when they came to be <hi>Nice,</hi> and <hi>Luxurious,</hi> and would have variety of coſtly Diſhes ſerved up at their Tables, many <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes</hi> followed: ſo it is obſervable in this Caſe; as long as Chriſtians contented themſelves with a <hi>Simple Religion,</hi> and a plain ſhort Creed, ſo long the Faith continued in a <hi>good</hi> ſtate; but when they came to be <hi>wanton,</hi> and would needs have this and that Point ſet out according to their <hi>Guſto,</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion became Sickly, and men Unſound, and by abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Learning, they were the leſs Virtuous, and the leſs Orthodox, but yet the more Techy and Imperious.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But (to come to our next Point) I know the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will by no means hear of this, that <hi>She</hi> has play'd any Tricks with the Ancient Faith, either by Adding to it, or by Taking from it, or by Embaſing it with any Novel Mixtures; nor indeed that it was <hi>Poſſible</hi> for Her to do it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that Singular Prerogative of an Un-erring
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50257:7"/>
Judgement which ſhe pretendeth to have above all Churches beſide. But this is a moſt vain and ridiculous conceit: for, becauſe ſhe was faithful once, it will no more follow, that ſhe hath been ſo ever ſince, then it will follow, that becauſe the Husbandman ſoweth Wheat in his Field, it ſhall bring forth no Tares; or, that becauſe a Child is Innocent upon his Baptiſm, he ſhall never grow up to be a Man of Sin; or, that becauſe a Virgin is yet unſpotted, ſhe will never turn Whore; or, that becauſe a man is yet in Health, he ſhall never be crazy; or, that becauſe a Town is yet free from the Plague, it ſhall never be viſited with it; or that we ſhall not be mortal, becauſe our Climate is Temperate, our Air good, our Phyſicians skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and our Food at preſent is wholſome. A long Tract of Time produceth many and great Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for one Generation paſſeth away, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comes; and many times we ſee, that the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities of men are not half ſo good as their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors were, and that Religion which was ſprightly and viſible in One Age, may be almoſt Loſt in another. Anciently the Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was Right, and her Biſhops were Wiſe and Holy men; but becauſe ſhe had this Honour in the <hi>Primitive</hi> times, was it impoſſible for her ever to loſe it? Was it Impoſſible, either for the Sheep in the fold to catch the Bane? or for the Shepherds to fall aſleep? or for Wolves to creep in unawares, or be encouraged and invited to come in at Noon-day? Why, look ye now, This is as great a piece of Non-ſence, as if you ſhould believe, that becauſe the City of <hi>London</hi> is now
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50257:8"/>
well ſtockt with a Knowing and Honeſt Clergy, it may not be as ill ſtockt with a pack of Illiterate and ill men, ſhould Times alter, and our Laws and Government be ſubverted. 'Tis true, Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed his Church, <hi>That the Gates of Hell ſhould not prevail againſt her:</hi> But this promiſe belongs not to any One <hi>particular National</hi> Church, but to the Church in <hi>General.</hi> 'Tis true alſo that Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Lo I am with you alwayes, even to the end of the world;</hi> but 'twas ſpoken to <hi>All</hi> the Apoſtles, and to all their Succeſſors for ever. 'Tis true likewiſe, that Chriſt prayed, <hi>That</hi> Peter<hi>'s Faith ſhould not fail:</hi> but this was a Perſonal reſpect to <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, but no ſecurity for thoſe that came after him; and we may well wonder, how it ſhould come into the head of any Papiſt to dream from that Text, that becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf did not utterly forſake the Faith, <hi>ergo,</hi> it was impoſſible for <hi>Marcellinus</hi> to become an Idolator, or for <hi>Eleutherius</hi> to turn Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſt, or for <hi>Liberius</hi> to fall off to the <hi>Arians,</hi> or for <hi>Honorius</hi> to be a Monothelite, or for <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> to turn <hi>Neſtorian,</hi> or for Pope <hi>John</hi> (the 23d. of that name) to teach, That there is no Future ſtate of Happineſs, nor any Reſurrection of the dead? And yet we have proved it upon them, that theſe things were done and taught, and that the Faith of theſe and other Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> hath actually failed either in whole, or in a very great part. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> gave her this warning, <hi>Be not high minded, but fear, Rom.</hi> 11. 20. and when he beſought them, to mark ſuch as <hi>cauſed diviſions and offences contrary to the doctrine which they had learned,</hi> Rom. 16. 17. either
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50257:8"/>
the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was then in danger of being tainted with Scandalous Principles, and of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing from the Truth, and of Falling from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God; or elſe the Apoſtle was an Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent man, and ill adviz'd, to give them ſuch Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs admonitions, and to tell them of danger when there was none.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But not to argue any longer at this rate. If it be made appear, that the Primitive Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Actually</hi> corrupted and alter'd, that will undeniably prove the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of that thing. And becauſe this is the main point in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, which (if proved) will at once take away all their pleas of an Infallible Spirit, all their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to Antiquity, all their Arguments againſt our Reformation, and all thoſe Inſinuations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they beguile Ignorant and Unwary men, I muſt deſire your patience while I inſiſt ſomewhat large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and particularly upon it. And for proof hereof I might take notice of one Modern Principle in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which doth plainly <hi>Intimate</hi> and <hi>Argue</hi> a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> out of their own mouths, that they have alter'd the <hi>Old Faith;</hi> for the Principle is this, <hi>That it lies in the power of their Church, not only to Declare New Articles of Faith,</hi> but to <hi>Make and Conſtitute</hi> New Creeds, and to Impoſe them as neceſſary to Salvation. The moſt Learned Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> hath ſhewed this againſt them in his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Diſſwaſive from Popery, wherein he obſerves too, that when Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth iſſued out his Bull againſt <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> and condemned him, he condemned him for teaching this, among other things, That it is not in the power of the Church
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50257:9"/>
or Pope to make Articles of Faith. Now, ſaith my Learned and Judicious Author rightly,<q> It is not Credible they would publiſh ſuch Invidious and Ill-ſounding Doctrine to no purpoſe, and to ſerve no End; therefore, it may without further Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence be believed by all Diſcerning perſons, that they have <hi>Need</hi> of this Doctrine, or it would not have been taught, and that conſequently without more ado it may be concluded, that ſome of their Articles are parts of this New faith.</q> But I ſhall wave this for Brevity-ſake; and ſo I ſhall wave alſo many Teſtimonies of ſome of the Ancients, which are uſually and with good Reaſon brought to prove the plain Innovations in Religion, which are now Taught and Practiſed in the Roman Church. I am willing to take a ſhorter courſe (and that which will bring me very home to them) to demonſtrate that they have alter'd and adulterated the <hi>Primitive</hi> Faith, even of their <hi>own</hi> Church: and this I ſhall ſhew by men of their own, and by uſing ſome Teſtimonies out of, and by making ſome Remarks upon ſome of the moſt conſiderable men, whom they own to have been Biſhops of their Church in the Primitive ages.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then, St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> are believed by them to have founded and built their Church: Nor can it well be denied, but they were both of them at <hi>Rome;</hi> and we may ſuppoſe the One to have been the Apoſtle of the Jewiſh, the other of the Gentile-Church there. But now, when the One calls the Scripture <hi>a ſure word of Prophecy, and requires us to take heed thereunto,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 19.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50257:9"/>
and when the other tells us, that <hi>The whole Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs, that the man of God may be Perfect, throughly furniſht unto all good works;</hi> How can we reconcile this with the late pretended Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Neceſſity of Tradition?</p>
            <p>When St. <hi>Peter</hi> requires us, <hi>To be ready alwayes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 15.</note> 
               <hi>to give an anſwer to every man that asketh us a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Hope that is in us;</hi> and when St <hi>Paul</hi>'s manner was <hi>To Reaſon with men out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 17. 3.</note> 
               <hi>opening and expounding the meaning of them;</hi> How can we reconcile this with thoſe Doctrines, touching the Neceſſity of Hiding the Scriptures from the Vulgar, and the Excellence of a Blind and Implicite Faith?</p>
            <p>When St. <hi>Peter</hi> affirms, <hi>That there is no Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>in any other, but in Chriſt only, and no other name under heaven given among men, whereby we can be ſaved;</hi> and when St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>That Chriſt was by his ſufferings conſecrated to be our High Prieſt, that He intercedeth for us, and is the One onely Mediator;</hi> how can we reconcile this with that Doctrine touching the Invocation of, and truſting in the Interceſſion and merits of Saints?</p>
            <p>When St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, <hi>That Chriſt Suffered Once</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 18. Heb. 7. 27. c. 9. 28. &amp; 10. 10.</note> 
               <hi>for Sins;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> agrees to it, <hi>That Chriſt offered up himſelf a Sacrifice Once, that he was Once offered, and that That offering of his body was once for All;</hi> How can we reconcile this with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine touching the daily Sacrificing of Chriſt in the Maſs?</p>
            <p>When St. <hi>Peter</hi> taught, <hi>That through the Grace</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50257:10"/>
               <hi>of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt we ſhall be ſaved;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> argued in this very Epiſtle to the Church of <note place="margin">Act. 5. 11. Rom. 11. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Rome, That if by Grace, then it is no more of works;</hi> How can we reconcile this with that Doctrine, about <hi>Earning</hi> and <hi>Meriting</hi> Heaven by the intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick value of our performances?</p>
            <p>When St. <hi>Peter</hi> would have us <hi>to call upon the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have us <hi>Pray with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and with the underſtanding alſo;</hi> How can we reconcile this with that Doctrine of Praying in an Unknown Tongue? A thing ſo directly repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Apoſtles order, as if it were done out of meer ſpight againſt 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>When One Apoſtle tells us, <hi>That we are redeemed not with corruptible things, as Silver and Gold;</hi> How can it conſiſt with that Doctrine, about redeeming Souls out of pain by Eight-penny Offerings, and a Luſty Legacy, as if our Saviour's <hi>Vae</hi> were to be removed, and the Goſpel were to run thus, <hi>Wo unto you that are</hi> Poor?</p>
            <p>And when the other Apoſtle ſo often calls the Solid Element in the Sacrament, <hi>Bread;</hi> how can it be Natural and Real <hi>Fleſh?</hi> and when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all men to eat of that <hi>Bread,</hi> and to drink of that Cup, how can we reconcile it with the Doctrine of Half-Communion, which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have confeſt to be contrary to the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Licet Chriſtus post coenam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituerit, &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is diſcipulis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtraverit ſub utraque ſpecie panis &amp; vini hoc venerabile ſacramentum, tamen hoc non obſtante, &amp;c.</hi> Concil. Conſtant. Seſſ. 13. <hi>Et ſimiliter, licet in Primitiva Eccleſia hujuſmodi Sacramentum reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peretur à fidelibus ſub utraque ſpecie, tamen, &amp;c.</hi> ibid.</note> of Chriſt, and againſt the practice of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50257:10"/>
Brieſly, when St. <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth, <hi>That the King is Supream,</hi> is it not New Doctrine, that He hath a <hi>Superior?</hi> yet this is a <hi>Popiſh Principle,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they be that believe it, that the King hath any above him, whether it be <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>People.</hi> And when we hear both theſe Great Apoſtles preaching up the Neceſſity of Obedience to the Government, the one peremptorily requiring us to <hi>Honour the King, and to ſubmit our ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lord's ſake;</hi> and the other preſſing this very home, particularly to the Romans, as if he had foreſeen that in after-ages men of the Romiſh Faith would prove Traytors, and to prevent it, if it were poſſible, we find him charging <hi>Every ſoul,</hi> [no Prieſt or Biſhop, or any other excepted] <hi>to be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> and that not only <hi>for wrath,</hi> but for <hi>conſcience ſake:</hi> I ſay, when theſe Doctrines are ſo Plain before us, may we not think, that they who have Sanctified Treaſon, and taught the world to be Baſe, did wholly over-look their Bibles? or had a greater veneration for a Curſed <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> or an <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> than for that noble pair of Apoſtles who were the Founders of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> To be ſure, we may as ſoon make the Artick and Antartick Poles to meet, as ever reconcile the <hi>Apoſtolick Faith</hi> with the <hi>Faith</hi> of our <hi>Romaniſts</hi> (though it be not Theirs <hi>onely)</hi> whereby it is made lawful, forſooth, to depoſe and deſtroy Princes, to abſolve Subjects from their Oaths of Allegiance (or to Interpret Oaths in a ſenſe that will ſerve their own Turn) to raiſe Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, to blow up Parliaments, to murder Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, whom they call Heretical, and Biſhops
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50257:11"/>
whom they call Malignant, or Prerogative-men, and for the advantage of a wretched cauſe, to do ſuch other Barbarities, as render <hi>Nero, Domitian</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian</hi> kind and good-natur'd Cut-throats in compariſon.</p>
            <p>I do not wonder, that the Papiſts care no more to look into the Scriptures, than a <hi>Monkey</hi> cares to look into a <hi>Glaſs,</hi> ſo very ugly is the <hi>Picture</hi> in it. But the <hi>Fathers,</hi> they ſay, are all on their ſide; and they ſay ſo the rather, becauſe their Writings are in Latine or Greek, which common people cannot underſtand, and which every <hi>knowing</hi> man hath not <hi>time</hi> to read. Now, though to confute this pretence, enough has been ſaid in the many Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies and Appeals for the Reformed Religion; yet let us Examine the Truth of this a little, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſide all other Ancient Writers, let us ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Old</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> themſelves, that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Apoſtles, will do them any good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now St. <hi>Clement</hi> is ſuppoſed immediately to have ſucceeded St. <hi>Peter</hi> as Biſhop of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hammond. Diſſert.</hi> 5.</note> Church at <hi>Rome;</hi> and we have extant two Epiſtles which go under his name, one whereof is <hi>confeſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> genuine, and it was written upon this occaſion: There had hapned in the Corinthian Church ſad Controverſies and Schiſms (ſuch as are now in the Church of <hi>England)</hi> about thlngs not appertaining to Salvation. Yet theſe ſmall matters occaſioned a huge breach; for the healing whereof <hi>Clement</hi> wrote them a moſt Excellent Epiſtle; yet not as their <hi>Primate,</hi> or <hi>Biſhop,</hi> but as a charitable good <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 71.</note> Neighbour; for he expreſt his deſires touching the Criminals at <hi>Corinth,</hi> that they would <hi>yield</hi> (or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50257:11"/>
be in Subjection) <hi>not to Us</hi> (ſaith He) but <hi>to the will of God.</hi> This makes it clear, that he claimed no Primacy or Juriſdiction over any Churches but his <hi>Own;</hi> and the whole Epiſtle is written, not in a Magiſterial ſtyle, ſavouring of any pretence of <hi>Dominion</hi> over the Corinthians, but is full of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs, Meekneſs, Intreaties, Prayers, Exhortations and Arguments from the Word of God; all which had been <hi>needleſs</hi> had He had any Superintending Power and Authority over them, for then he might (and we may well think, would) have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently paſt a <hi>Definitive</hi> Sentence, and determin'd the Controverſie without any more ado. But he ſends them to the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> as to the Rule which they were to judge things by; commends their knowledg of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> wiſhes them dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently <note place="margin">Pag. 68.</note> to look into the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and particularly <note place="margin">Pag. 58.</note> he recommends to them the firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> He tells them, <hi>That we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 61.</note> 
               <hi>not of our ſelves, nor by our wiſdome, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 41.</note> 
               <hi>or piety, or works (though we do them with ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and purity of heart) but by faith, and by the will and good pleaſure of God.</hi> He exhorteth them to <hi>ſubmit to their own Paſtors and Governors;</hi> and <note place="margin">Pag, 63.</note> tells them, that the Greater a man is, either for Knowledg or Goodneſs, the more Humble he ought to be. And in his other Epiſtle (which ſeems to be as genuine as the former) he admires the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note place="margin">V. <hi>Bevereg. Cod. vindicat.</hi> l. 2. c. 9.</note> of God to them, that they did no longer <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Stones, and Wood, and Gold, and Silver, and Braſs,</hi> the works of mens hands; and ſo intreats <note place="margin">Pag. 1.</note> them to Repent while they had <hi>Time</hi> to Repent, and while they had an opportunity of being
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50257:12"/>
healed; <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>after we are once gone out of This world we cannot make confeſſion of our Sins, or</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Repent of them</hi> (ſo as to be ſaved.) Here then let the world judge, whether they that make the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the <hi>Univerſal</hi> Paſtour of all Churches in the world, that ſuppreſs the uſe of the Holy Bible, that teach Blind Obedience, that talk of Salvation by their own Deſerts, that adore Images and Pictures, that preach the Doctrine of Purgatory, and pretend to ſhew us a Trick, how we may be ſaved, and how we may be delivered out of Torments <hi>after Death,</hi> though we die <hi>in Sin.</hi> Judge, I ſay, whether theſe men have not <hi>corrupted</hi> the Faith, and changed it to another thing from what it was in the dayes of St. <hi>Clement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Another of the old Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> was <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetus,</hi> in whoſe dayes that Controverſie aroſe, when the <hi>Lent</hi> Faſt ſhould conclude, and <hi>Eaſter</hi> be kept; ſome arguing that it ought to be kept on the day of the Jews Paſſeover (which was the Cuſtome in <hi>Aſia;)</hi> others, that it ſhould be kept on the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection-day, (which was the Cuſtome at <hi>Rome,</hi> and in other Churches.) Upon this, <hi>Polycarp</hi> (St. <hi>John</hi>'s Scholar) goes to <hi>Rome,</hi> and diſputes with <hi>Anicetus</hi> about this and other matters; but neither party convinced the other, and ſo after ſome little heats, they parted good friends, and in perfect charity, both of them having received the Holy Communion. Now can any man in his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. Eccleſ. Hiſt.</hi> l. 5. c. 24.</note> Wits believe, that in thoſe dayes the Popes Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was thought Infallible? or that <hi>Anicetus</hi> himſelf thought it ſo, when he neither Preſumed to determine the Controverſie, nor could do it,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50257:12"/>
nor was able to ſatisfie any of the Eaſtern Biſhops?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Within a while after Him ſucceeded <hi>Eleuthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> in whoſe days the Doctrines of <hi>Montanus</hi> made a filthy ſtir; and to ſtifle the ſpreading of that Plague the Gallican Church wrote Letters into <hi>Aſia,</hi> and another they ſent to the Pope himſelf, admoniſhing him to follow the things which made for Peace: For <hi>Tertullian</hi> is witneſs, that the Pope <note place="margin">Tertul adv. Prax. in initio.</note> was infected with <hi>Montaniſm.</hi> But yet ſo it was, that through Fear on the One hand, and through the ſolicitations of <hi>Praxeas</hi> on the other, he was fain to Reject <hi>Montanus</hi> and his followers. And can we imagine, that the world then counted <hi>Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius</hi>'s Judgment <hi>Infallible,</hi> when they found him to have been <hi>Haeretical?</hi> or that <hi>Eleutherius</hi> himſelf thought he could not Err, when he <hi>Condemned</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſm, which before he had <hi>Embraced?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Pope <hi>Victor</hi> was the next, and of him I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe two things: Firſt, That whereas it was provided by an Old Canon of the Church, <hi>That every Nation ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Can. Apoſt.</hi> 34.</note> 
               <hi>their Own Primate, and count him their Head, and do nothing without bis Order,</hi> Pope <hi>Victor</hi> own'd the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of this Canon, and claimed no Primacy over <hi>Polycrates</hi> (the Metropolitan of the <hi>Procon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſular Aſia)</hi> when he wrote to him about calling a Synod to conſider of the Paſchal Controverſie. For <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit</hi> Polycra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes <hi>ad Vict. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. Hiſt. Eccl.</hi> l. 5. c. 24.</note> though the Popes now challenge a power of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning all Councils, by virtue of their pretended Primacy over all Churches, yet it was not ſo in Pope <hi>Victor</hi>'s dayes; for he did entreat and beſeech <hi>Polycrates</hi> that He would call a Synod of Biſhops
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50257:13"/>
               <hi>himſelf.</hi> Secondly, That when <hi>Victor</hi> purpoſed to Anathematize the Aſiatick Churches, for not complying with his Humour, <hi>Irenaus</hi> and many other Biſhops dealt very roundly and roughly with him, ſo that he was <hi>forced</hi> to <hi>Alter</hi> his purpoſe. Whence it appears, that the Popes in thoſe dayes were ſo far from conceiving themſelves to be <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream,</hi> or free from a poſſibility of <hi>Erring,</hi> that they ſtood in awe of their Fellow-Biſhops, that could upon occaſion <hi>Ruffle</hi> with them, and make them keep the Peace, and bind them to their good behaviour.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I might ſhew too how St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> rated both thoſe Popes in his time, <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Stephen:</hi> but I forbear to gather any more inſtances of that nature, becauſe it is ſo well known, that for near 600 years after Chriſt the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> never had the Title of <hi>Univerſal Paſtors</hi> of the Church, till the dayes of <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third, and he gat it baſely, and by the grant of that Bloody wretch <hi>Phocas,</hi> who had murder'd the Emperor <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and all his Children, and had no way to ſecure himſelf but by giving the Pope a <hi>Title</hi> that pleaſed him; and ever ſince our Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be the <hi>Landlords</hi> of all God's Vineyard, inſtead of being <hi>Labourers</hi> in it; or rather have been <hi>Wolves</hi> inſtead of <hi>Shepherds:</hi> and it is obſervable, that the <hi>Donor</hi> of this title was a Bloody <hi>Tyrant</hi> and <hi>Traytor;</hi> and you may gueſs at the Father by the Child, for generally ſince, the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed</hi> and <hi>Treaſon</hi> hath run along in the veins of the <hi>Donees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. To which I ſhall only add the Teſtimony of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50257:13"/>
one Pope more, not that he is the next in <hi>Order,</hi> but becauſe 'tis moſt <hi>pertinent</hi> to this point; and 'tis the Teſtimony of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, who ſpeaking of the Title of <hi>Univerſal Biſhop</hi> of the Church, doth up and down in his Epiſtles call it a Title of <hi>Novelty, Error, Blaſphemy, Impiety, full of poiſon, contrary to the Ancient Canons, to the Holy Goſpel, and to god himſelf, and the fore-runner of Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. And as touching the point of Infallibility, Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the Sixth did plainly aſſert (and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> owns it) that the Pope might be guilty of down-right Hereſy, and the Cardinal doth confeſs that for above 1400 years his judgment was not eſteemed Infallible; and the plain truth is, he was never complemented under that notion, till he got the <hi>Empire</hi> over Princes, and the <hi>Preferments</hi> of the Church into his clutches. <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> (who himſelf was a Pope) gave this reaſon, why the Clergy made him Infallible above all Councils, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could reward 'em well with fat promotions, which Councils could not,</hi> and had he ſued for this Title <hi>in farma Pauperis,</hi> and without a good <hi>Fee</hi> in his hand, either his Cauſe would not have been pleaded at all, or, by the Verdict of all the Fathers, he would have been preſently Caſt; but in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> 'tis <hi>Money that doth all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been the longer upon theſe points, becauſe they are ſome of the <hi>main</hi> and moſt <hi>material</hi> points that are in controverſie between us, which if they would but part with, many other conceits (if not all) would ſoon fall to the ground, which are now held up chiefly by the <hi>uſurped</hi> Authority of the Church.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50257:14"/>
9. I will not except the conceit of <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gelaſ. de dua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus naturis in Chriſto.</note> (which if it were Ruin'd, would, like the Dragons tail, ſweep down a great many other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired Fancies with it.) For as touching our Faith in this particular, we appeal to another of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Biſhops of <hi>Rome, Gelaſius</hi> by name, who wrote an excellent Book which is yet extant, and he wrote it upon this occaſion. The Heretick <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiches</hi> and his followers did believe that though at. <hi>firſt</hi> Chriſt had <hi>two</hi> diſtinct Natures, yet upon the <hi>Union</hi> of 'em, the Humane nature was wholly converted into the Divine, ſo that his Humanity <hi>ceaſed,</hi> and was <hi>abſorpt</hi> and <hi>turn'd</hi> into the ſubſtance of his <hi>Divinity</hi> (juſt as our Adverſaries pretend, that the Bread in the H. Euchariſt ceaſeth and is turn'd into the ſubſtance of Chriſt's Fleſh.) Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> undertook the maintenance of the Catholic Faith againſt theſe Hereticks, and (which is well to be obſerved) to prove the real exiſtence of our Saviour's Humane nature, he draws an Argument from the then received Doctrine concerning the nature of the Elements in the Euchariſt: And his words I render thus. <q>
                  <hi>Verily the Sacraments of Chriſts Body and Blood, which we receive, are a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine thing, becauſe by means thereof we are made partakers of the divine Nature; and yet the ſubſtance or Nature of the Bread and Wine doth not ceaſe to be: And indeed it is the Image and Similitude of Chriſts Body and Blood, which is repreſented in this Myſterious action. It is evident enough therefore that we muſt think the ſame of our Lord himſelf, which we profeſs, celebrate and take in the Image of him, that as</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50257:14"/>
                  <hi>theſe Elements by the operation of the Holy Spirit, do paſs into this, that is a Divine condition, ſtill nevertheleſs remaining in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">So I conceive the words of <hi>Gelaſius</hi> ſhould be read, <hi>Sic illud ipſum (eſt) myſterium prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipale, cujus nobis efficientiam virtutemque veraciter reprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentant (Scil. Sacramenta) ex quibus conſtat (propriè perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentibus) quia <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Chriſtum, integrum, verumque permanere demonſtrant.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>of their own nature; ſo is the Principal myſtery it ſelf, the efficiency and virtue whereof is truly repreſented unto us by the Elements which truly and properly remaining ſtill the ſame, it is manifeſt that they ſhew one, entire and true Chriſt to remain in the union of both natures.</hi>
               </q> From theſe words of <hi>Gelaſius</hi> it is clear, that the <hi>real</hi> union of both Chriſts natures is the Principal myſtery which is here repreſented; and that this is repreſented by the <hi>Sacramental</hi> union between the Bread and the Wine, and the Body and Blood of Chriſt. And hence he concludes, that the <hi>Nature</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Humanity</hi> doth ſtill remain, becauſe the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of the <hi>Elements</hi> doth ſtill remain. But this would not have been <hi>Argumentative</hi> or <hi>Concluſive</hi> at all, had not the Church then believed, that the <hi>nature</hi> of the Bread and Wine is not <hi>aboliſht</hi> in the Sacrament; for 'tisfrom that <hi>Principle,</hi> that received and <hi>common</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that he argues againſt thoſe deceivers: So that if <hi>We</hi> are Hereticks for denying the doctrine of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> himſelf was an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <hi>alſo;</hi> for Teaching that which is the Faith of all Proteſtants: But indeed neither was he, nor are we to be blamed; for it was the Faith not of Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> alone, but of all the Primitive Catholicks.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Should I now tell you, that the ſame <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> condemned the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Comperimus autem, quod qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſumpta tantummodo corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſacri portione à Calice Sacri cruoris abſtineani. Qui procul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubio (quoniam neſcio quâ ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitione docentur obſtringi) aut Integra Sacramenta percipiant; aut ab integris arceantur, quia diviſio unus ejuſdemque myſterii ſine Grandi Sacrilegio non poteſt provenire. Papa Gelas. in Gratiani Decret. de Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat distinct.</hi> 2. c. 12.</note> of the Sacrament <hi>in one kind</hi> only, as contrary to the uſage of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50257:15"/>
Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf in his time; that <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt condemned all Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of any Creature; that St. <hi>Gregory</hi> diſclaimed the worſhiping of <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Pictures,</hi> and overthrew the Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and ſo go on ſearching into the times of old, and making ſuch other Collections, as 'tis no very hard matter to <note place="margin">Leo <hi>ſer</hi> 2. <hi>in Nativit.</hi>
               </note> make, I ſhould ſoon return more than a <hi>Full Jury</hi> of the Primitive Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> (and thoſe <hi>good</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Greg or. <hi>Ep. ad Seren.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>men</hi> and <hi>true,</hi> in compariſon) to try and clear this grand point, that the Errors of the modern Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Et in</hi> 7 Job. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> which we have rejected are ſuch, as are not to be reconciled with the Primitive Faith of the <hi>very Roman Church;</hi> which was the third thing I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to ſhow.</p>
            <p>4. But we will forbear to walk further among the Monuments of the dead. Inſtead of that, we will, in the next place take a ſhort view of the vanity of their Pretences, who charge us with <hi>Noveltie, Hereſie,</hi> and <hi>Schiſme,</hi> for imbracing and ſticking to that Reformation, which by the wonderful good Providence of God hath been wrought in many parts of the Chriſtian world, and more eſpecially <hi>here</hi> in this Realm. Had we broached any Doctrines which are really <hi>New,</hi> we had been guilty of <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</hi> Had we violated the integrity of the Apoſtles Creed, we had been guilty of Hereſie; or had we bid defiance to the Communion of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick and Apoſtolick Church, we had been guilty of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and our condition would be ſad. But the old Sages of the Church, and our own Conſciences do bear us witneſs, that in every of theſe reſpects
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50257:15"/>
we are not only <hi>Innocent</hi> but <hi>Righteous;</hi> for our Faith beareth the ſame date with Chriſtianity, and we have forſaken the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in no <hi>material point,</hi> but where ſhe hath for ſaken the <hi>Ancient</hi> Church, and indeed her <hi>own Primitive ſelf.</hi> And how are we to blame, if we have done this, tho it be againſt her humour? Is it not very hard that the Governours of a Family ſhall not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to cleanſe their <hi>own</hi> houſe from filth and cobwebs, becauſe the next Neighbour will chuſe to let his habitation ly like a Dunghill? or is it not unreaſonable that one Church muſt not be allowed to be a cleanly Matron, becauſe another is reſolved to be a dirty Slut? why, thus ſtands the caſe between us and our Imperious and Unconſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Neighbours. Our Biſhops (as to their juſt Authority) ſtand upon the ſame Level with the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo do all the Biſhops in the world beſide: And this is according to the <hi>34th</hi> Apoſtolick Canon. Now, if he will not ſuffer a Beeſome to come near his door, the fault is not ours (and much good may his <hi>ſtye</hi> do him, ſo he do but ly in it <hi>quietly:)</hi> but neither ought it to be an offence to him, if our Prelates have taken the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>faireſt</hi> opportunity they could take, to ſweep our Church, and ſet it to rights, as all the Churches of God were of old. They commonly ask us where our Faith was before <hi>Luther?</hi> and we ſay, <hi>'twas in the Creed,</hi> which our Anceſtors <hi>before Luther</hi>'s time believed, as well as we do Now; and as far as they believed <hi>that,</hi> ſo far they were <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Catholicks;</hi> and ſo far we allow our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> to be Chriſtians and Catholicks too: For this is the <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>common</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:50257:16"/>
Faith of all Chriſtians. But before the Reformation, many <hi>Errors</hi> did bear this Faith <hi>company,</hi> and made the Table <hi>fowl</hi> wherein the <hi>Creed</hi> was written; and when we took it down to cleanſe it, we only bruſht off the <hi>duſt</hi> from it, ſo that ſtill our <hi>Faith</hi> was and is the <hi>ſame,</hi> though our Errors in other matters are thrown out of doors. They ask us, where our Church was before King <hi>Hen.</hi> the <hi>8th?</hi> and we tell 'em 'twas here in <hi>England,</hi> where it is ſtill. But before King <hi>Henry</hi>'s time 'twas <hi>abuſed</hi> and fill'd with <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> and <hi>Legends,</hi> and a great deal of <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> and unlawfull Stuff, which either the ignorance or the knavery and ſecular deſignes of ſome Prieſts hadfoiſted in (and, which we hope, God in mercy did pardon to our fore-fathers, who did not <hi>know</hi> the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfullneſs</hi> of thoſe Wares.) And when in King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s dayes a <hi>Reformation</hi> was begun, and after was compleated, we did not pull down the Church over our heads, but only flung out of it ſuch things as had been amiſs in it; ſo that our Church is the <hi>ſame</hi> ſtill, only then it was <hi>Naſty,</hi> and now it is <hi>Neat;</hi> We neither deſtroyed the <hi>old</hi> fabrick, nor built a <hi>New</hi> one; but we cleanſed that which <hi>was,</hi> and purged the Sanctuary from its Pollutions, letting the Pillars and the Walls, the Creed, the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> and what elſe was <hi>neceſſary</hi> or <hi>fitting</hi> for God's Worſhip, to ſtand ſtill as they did, and indeed better. Now if this was a Crime, truly it might have been laid to our Saviour's own charge, when he went about to Reform thoſe abuſes and innovations which had crept into the Jewiſh Church by the Artifice of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> as theſe did into our Church by the help of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50257:16"/>
the <hi>Prieſts.</hi> Did he not tell them, <hi>that from the beginning it was not ſo?</hi> and did he not thereby direct them to <hi>Primitive</hi> practice, as the <hi>Rule of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation?</hi> and would it have been a good plea againſt him, ſhould the Jews have ſaid, Thus we have formerly believed, and done from the days of yore, therefore to teach otherwiſe is to be guilty of <hi>Novelty</hi> and <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and to ſet up <hi>another</hi> Church? or would it have been a ſufficient plea againſt his Diſciples, thoſe great Reformers of the <hi>world,</hi> ſhould the Phariſees have demanded of them, <hi>where was your Church before Chriſt?</hi> is it not a Muſhrome of yeſterday? and had not the anſwer been eaſie, that they had brought Religion to that purity which God anciently intended? why this is our caſe, that we have Reſtor'd the Catholic <hi>Faith which was once delivered unto the Saints,</hi> and have laid aſide that <hi>Hay</hi> and <hi>Stuble</hi> and <hi>Traſh</hi> which had been piled upon this Foundation; and if the Purifying of the Antient Faith be <hi>Hereſie,</hi> if the cleanſing of our Church from Litter be <hi>Innovation,</hi> and if the profeſſing and practiſing of thoſe things that were in the Apoſtolick Ages be <hi>Schiſm,</hi> then we muſt own our ſelves guilty; but own too, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> were our Precedents, only they had <hi>Miracles</hi> to ſpeak on their ſide, we have (beſide the Cannon of H. <hi>Scripture)</hi> the Books of the <hi>Old Fathers</hi> to ſpeak on our behalf, and the credit of the <hi>Old Roman Church</hi> it ſelf to teſtifie for us; and to thoſe Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies we Appeal.</p>
            <p>5. Laſtly, what would not the Romaniſts give, could they at half ſuch an eaſie rate be able to juſtify thoſe <hi>evil methods,</hi> whereby they have expreſt their impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50257:17"/>
enmity againſt Us, for no other reaſon but becauſe We have told them the truth, and will not be perſwaded to ſhake hands with them in their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties? if the ſpirit of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> be the ſpirit of Chriſt; If the <hi>calling for Fire from Heaven</hi> (or the fetching of it from Hell) be utterly incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the temper of a Chriſtian; If our <hi>Holy</hi> o <hi>Lords Kingdom be not of this world;</hi> If the weapons of our warfare be not Carnal; and if that be the <hi>only true wiſdom from above</hi> which is <hi>Pure, Peaceable</hi> and <hi>Gentle:</hi> Then they have reaſon to bluſh and hide their faces (but that <hi>Impudenoe</hi> is the Daughter of <hi>Lewdneſs</hi> and <hi>Apoſtacy)</hi> who talk ſo much of their Catholick <hi>Faith,</hi> which hath nothing to ſupport it but their Catholick <hi>Villanies.</hi> Even as to <hi>this</hi> point too, if we look into the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Faith of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, we ſhall find it to have been expreſt by <hi>ſelf-denial, by bearing the Croſs,</hi> by <hi>Subjection unto Princes,</hi> and <hi>ſuffering Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to that degree, that a great number of their <hi>primitive Biſhops</hi> were ſucceſſively made ſo many glorious <hi>Martyrs.</hi> And how comes it to paſs, that whereas <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> was once a great part of that Churches <hi>Honour;</hi> at laſt the lawfulneſs of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> ſhould get in to be part of her <hi>Creed!</hi> For, are not theſe her Doctrines, That ſhe can diveſt Princes of their Regalities? that ſhe can (without Sinning) expoſe and Sacrifice their very lives? that ſhe can free her Children from all the moſt Sacred tyes of ſubjection? that all the Kingdomes of the world and the glory of them are hers, and that ſhe can give them to whomſoever ſhe pleaſeth (as if ſhe had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50257:17"/>
been trucking for a bargin with the Divel <hi>himſelf?)</hi> That men by being Hereticks (in her account) do <hi>ipſo facto</hi> forfeit all their Rights Sacred and Civil? and that to Kill and Butcher ſuch Hereticks is an act highly Meritorious of Salvation? let her <hi>deny</hi> theſe Doctrines, if ſhe <hi>can,</hi> or Diſclaim them, if ſhe <hi>dare;</hi> but you ſhall never find her ſo Honeſt, becauſe ſhe is Conſcious to her ſelf, that did ſhe not hallow theſe and the like Principles to keep the world in awe, her Court would ſoon want Attendants, and her cauſe an Advocate. And is there not a moſt perfect <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> between her lewd <hi>Faith,</hi> and her villanous <hi>Practice,</hi> whereby ſhe hath rowled her Garments, not in her own, but in the blood of Peers, Prelates, Princes; an unaccountable Hoſt of Martyrs, whoſe blood ſhe hath abundantly ſhed over the whole Chriſtian and Reformed world? witneſs the ſtreams drawn in the upper and lower <hi>Germany,</hi> and in the neighbouring Countries; witneſs the former Maſſacrees in <hi>France,</hi> and the Freſh Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there now, which is likely enough in a little while to end in Blood too. Witneſs the Barbarous Executions in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which are not quite loſt out of our own memories: And, witneſs the continual Diabolical attempts which have been made againſt This Kingdom in every age ſince the beginning of the Reformation; as the Troubles under King <hi>Hen.</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> the Inſurrections under King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> the huge <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>Offerings</hi> by <hi>fire</hi> under <hi>Q. Mary;</hi> the Spaniſh Invaſion, and Domeſtick Conſpiracies under <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> and (which we commemorate our deliverance from <hi>THIS DAY)</hi> the <hi>Powder-Plot</hi> under King <hi>James,</hi> when nothing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50257:18"/>
would ſatisfie thoſe <hi>Sanguinary Catholicks,</hi> but the deſtruction of the whole <hi>Race Royal</hi> and of the Repreſentatives and Flower of the whole Realm. And (to ſay no more) witneſs that <hi>Helliſh</hi> and <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Conſpiracy,</hi> which hath been <hi>lately Levelled</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Gentleſt</hi> and <hi>Kindeſt</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> againſt our <hi>Laws, Goverment, Religion,</hi> and the Common ſafety of us all.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God that hath <hi>Providentially</hi> and <hi>Marvellously</hi> brought to light the hidden things of darkneſs. Bleſſed be God for the Miraculous Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance which his own Goodneſs and Immediate hand wrought for us This Day. And for ever bleſſed be his name, that <hi>ſince that Time</hi> he hath kept us all along out of the hands of all our enemies, that he hath delivered us <hi>yet,</hi> and we hope <hi>will</hi> deliver us yet <hi>ſtill.</hi> And God of his mercy grant, that as our <hi>Faith</hi> is <hi>Pure, Primitive,</hi> and <hi>Holy,</hi> ſo we may ſtudy not only to <hi>Contend</hi> for it, but to <hi>Adorn</hi> it too, by the Simplicity of our hearts, by the Unity of our Affections, by a perfectly Honeſt and Peaceable deportment, and by all the Neceſſary and Laudable inſtances of a Godly and Righteous Converſation; that <hi>Our</hi> Faith alſo may be ſpoken of and renowned throughout the whole world, and that the God of mercy and compaſſion may Protect and bleſs us for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
